<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two olive trees: or, The Lords two anointed ones, which alwayes stand before Him, the ruler of the whole earth, Zach. 4. Described also Rev. 11. by the names of [brace] two witnesses, two olive trees, two candlesticks, two prophets. [brace] And shewing what they are in their own true nature, differing from all the new fancied ones, and in what manner they alwayes prophesie. How they are said to finish their testimony. How they were to be killed by the Beast, and when. How long their corps should lie in the streets of the Beasts great citie, dead and unburied. And when the spirit of life from God should enter into them, and they stand upon their feet again. And what great things should follow after the same to the end, and thence for ever. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>I. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E270_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212360</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">123383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E270[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two olive trees: or, The Lords two anointed ones, which alwayes stand before Him, the ruler of the whole earth, Zach. 4. Described also Rev. 11. by the names of [brace] two witnesses, two olive trees, two candlesticks, two prophets. [brace] And shewing what they are in their own true nature, differing from all the new fancied ones, and in what manner they alwayes prophesie. How they are said to finish their testimony. How they were to be killed by the Beast, and when. How long their corps should lie in the streets of the Beasts great citie, dead and unburied. And when the spirit of life from God should enter into them, and they stand upon their feet again. And what great things should follow after the same to the end, and thence for ever. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>I. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the Christian reader" signed: I.E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Zechariah --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123383:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TWO OLIVE TREES: OR, The Lords two Anointed ones, which alwayes ſtand before Him, the Ruler of the whole Earth, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Deſcribed alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. by the names Of
<list>
                  <item>Two Witneſſes,</item>
                  <item>Two Olive Trees,</item>
                  <item>Two Candleſticks,</item>
                  <item>Two Prophets.</item>
                  <item>And ſhewing
<list>
                        <item>What they are in their owne true nature, differing from all the new fancied ones, and in what manner they alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.</item>
                        <item>How they are ſaid to finiſh their teſtimony.</item>
                        <item>How they were to be killed by the Beaſt, and when.</item>
                        <item>How long their corps ſhould lie in the ſtreets of the Beaſts great Citie, dead and unburied.</item>
                        <item>And when the Spirit of life from God ſhould enter into them, and they ſtand upon their feet again.</item>
                        <item>And what great things ſhould follow after the ſame to the end, and thence for ever.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:123383:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123383:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough there are many opinions at this day on foot concerning the <hi>two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of God,</hi> deſcribed in <hi>Zach.</hi> 4. by the names of <hi>two Olive Trees,</hi> and <hi>the two anointed ones which ſtand before the Ruler of the earth:</hi> as alſo by the names of <hi>two Candleſtickes,</hi> and <hi>two Prophets, Rev. 11.</hi> and much queſtionings and doubts made about them, who and what they ſhould be, &amp;c. And that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may ſeem too bold, eſpecially among men ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wiſe, and in ſo great and difficult a cauſe as this is, to ſpeak or publiſh what I have heard, or may ſeem to underſtand; yet ſeeing things to be as they are, I ſuppoſe I may with leave venture to doe it.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, the matter hath already long before this time very truly been unfolded, by ſome whoſe ſhooes I am not worthy to beare, if we could ſee it; but that wee are ſo naturally blind concerning the truth, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſeek out new inventions of our own, and ſuch as may ſeeme beſt to ſuit with the preſent times and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the people; and withall ſerve to make for
<pb facs="tcp:123383:3"/>
our temporall advantages, which we are to repent of, as being very great evils.</p>
            <p>That which I ſhall doe herein, is onely this, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſome things a little more plainly to the plainer ſort of Chriſtians like my ſelfe, to remove ſome obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and cleare ſome doubts. After which, I hope it will not remain to the meek &amp; humble in heart, a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter altogether ſo obſcure and unknowne, what the <hi>two Olive Trees, the Lords two Witneſſes, his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed ones,</hi> are, in their own true nature, differing from all the new invented ones, which ſome would have us to entertain for them, or beſides them.</p>
            <p>I requeſt the Chriſtian Reader therefore to excuſe my boldneſſe herein, ſeeing it is his good that I ſeek, as well as my owne, deſiring that we may all eſcape the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and evils of the times, and be led by the Spirit of truth into all truth, and ſo Walke in the ſame to the praiſe of God, and our owne ſalvation, which is now neere at hand to be revealed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So I reſt,</hi> His Chriſtan friend, <hi>I. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur.</hi> Iohn Downam.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:123383:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TWO OLIVE TREES: OR, The Lords two anointed Ones, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4. Deſcribed alſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. by the names Of
<list>
                  <item>Two Witneſſes,</item>
                  <item>Two Olive Trees,</item>
                  <item>Two Candleſticks,</item>
                  <item>Two Prophets.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>REV. 11. verſ. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And there was given me a Reed like unto a Rod, and the Angel that ſtood by me, ſaid, Riſe, and meaſure the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore the Lord begins to deſcribe his two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> requireth his ſervant <hi>Iohn</hi> to take a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of his Church of Saints, the ſpirituall houſe of God, conſiſting of living ſtones, built on the chiefe Corner Stone, Jeſus Chriſt, (they being the holy Prieſthood, who offer up ſpirituall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices acceptable to God by him) which hee ſignifieth by the Temple of Jeruſalem, and the Altar of Incenſe that was in the ſame, whereinto the Prieſts onely might enter through the vaile, to ſacrifice and adore.</p>
               <p>Theſe onely are they that the Lord will have to bee meaſured,
<pb facs="tcp:123383:4"/>
and taken notice of, as being his part and portion, his Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle wherein he will dwell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl> But the Court which is without the Temple, cast out, and meaſure not, for it is given to the Gentiles, and the holy Citie ſhall they tread under foot fourty and two months.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BY the outer Court of the Temple, which <hi>John</hi> is bidden to caſt out, and not meaſure, wee are to underſtand the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon outward unregenerate Chriſtians, who (eſpecially after the diſperſion of the true Spouſe of Chriſt from her primitive viblſie eſtate) ſhould become many in number, and attaine to great authority and power in the outward ſtate of the Church, and take upon them, and aſſume unto themſelves as if they were the very true Church and Spouſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe, who notwithſtanding all this their outward profeſſion and taking much upon them, are but Gentiles in heart, full of all uncleanneſſe and abominations (reſembled here by the outward Court of the Temple where the Brazen Altar was, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into all the people of Iſrael might enter and ſacrifice) are they whom the Lord commandeth to be caſt out, and forbiddeth to be meaſured, or accounted of as being any part of his portion, or inheritance.</p>
               <p>And whereas theſe Gentiles are ſaid to tread the holy Citie under foot fourty and two months, is foreſhewed, that they ſhould perſecute, kill and keep downe out of ſight, the true Spouſe and her children, who are here deſcribed by the name of the holy Citie, becauſe they are the Tabernacle and Sanctuary of God, wherein hee will dwell for ever. And that this they were to doe for the ſpace of fourty and two months, which are to be underſtood months of yeares, taking every day of each month for a yeare, according to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 3.</hi>
                     </bibl> And I will give to my two witneſſes, and they ſtall propheſie a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes, clothed in ſackcloth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BY which words the Lord by his Angel gives to his ſervant <hi>Iohn,</hi> and unto all his Church of Saints, to underſtand, that although thoſe Gentiles unto whom the outward Court was to bee given, ſhould tread the holy City of Saints under foot ſo
<pb facs="tcp:123383:4"/>
long as fourty and two months of yeares; yet nevertheleſſe hee would ſo give unto his two Witneſſes, that they ſhould prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie all the while, even every one of the dayes of thoſe months, which according to the account of the Hebrewes, who had thirty dayes to every month, and twelve months to every yeare, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, according as the Lord doth here alſo intend it, a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore years. And ſheweth alſo that their manner of propheſying ſhould be, as cloathed in Sack-cloth, that is to ſay, in mourning; for ſo in the ſame kinde of habit they always propheſied, although it would be now much more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, by reaſon of the abundant cruelties of their enemies, who ſhould for their word and teſtimony ſake, perſecute thoſe that in the evidence of the Spirit, and the teares of true repentance, faith and patience, teſtified the ſame againſt their Gentiliſme, hypocriſie, and lies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl> Theſe are the two Olive Trees, and the two Candleſticks, ſtanding in the preſence of the Lord of the earth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre the Lord now begins to declare unto his ſervant <hi>Iohn,</hi> and ſo unto all the Saints, what his two Witneſſes are in their own true nature, in ſaying, <hi>Theſe are the two Olive Trees, and the two Candleſticks ſtanding, &amp;c. The two,</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>the onely two,</hi> and the very ſame two Olive branches, the <hi>two anointed ones,</hi> or Sonnes of oyle ſhewed before unto the Prophet <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary,</hi> which ſtood fructifying continually before the Ruler of the whole earth, not onely in the Prophets time, but alſo long before his dayes, and ſince, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.14. for ſo much doe the words clearly imply, ſhewing that they were not two new ones not yet ſprung up, but thoſe that were of old; the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring us as it were to the teſtimony of the Prophet, which we are further to conſider of.</p>
               <p>As firſt, where he ſaith, <hi>I have looked, and behold a Candleſticke all of gold, with a bole upon the top of it, and his ſeven lamps thereon, and ſeven pipes to the ſeven lamps which were upon the top thereof. And two Olive Trees by it, one upon the right ſide of the bole, and the other upon the left ſide thereof,</hi> verſ. 2.3.</p>
               <p>So the Prophet having ſeen theſe things, deſires to know what they were, and the Angel anſwered him, ſaying, <hi>This is the word of the Lord unto Zerubbabel, ſaying, Not by might, nor by power, but by
<pb facs="tcp:123383:5"/>
my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel thou ſhalt become <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>plain, and he ſhall bring forth the head ſtone thereof with ſhouting, crying, Grace, grace unto it,</hi> verſ. 3.4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>And the word of the Lord came again unto the Prophet, ſaying, The hands of Zerubbabel have laid the foundation of this houſe, and his hands ſhall alſo finiſh it, and thou ſhalt know that the Lord of hoſts hath ſent me unto you. For who hath deſpiſed the day of ſmall things? for they ſhall rejoyce, and ſhall ſee the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel, with thoſe ſeven, they are the eyes of the Lord, which run to and fro through the whole earth,</hi> verſ. 8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Although the Prophet had ſeen and heard all theſe things, yet was he not ſatisfied concerning the two Olive trees, but queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons again, ſaying, <hi>What be theſe two Olive trees upon the right ſide of the Candleſtick, and upon the left ſide thereof?</hi> verſ. 11.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>What be theſe two Olive branches which through the two golden pipes empty the oyle out of themſelves into the gold?</hi> ver 12.</p>
               <p>And the Angel anſwered him, ſaying, <hi>Knoweſt thou not what theſe be? And he ſaid, No, my Lord.</hi> Then ſaid the Angel unto him, <hi>Theſe are the two anointed ones that ſtand by the Lord of the whole earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Prophet underſtood every thing, and accordingly as they were declared unto him, he writ them downe, to the end that other Saints alſo might underſtand the ſame.</p>
               <p>And yet (for all this, and notwithſtanding all that Chriſt hath revealed and ſpoken by his Angell unto his ſervant <hi>Iohn,</hi> and hee left written to us) it remaines in doubt, and is ſtill a great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion with many at this day, what the two Witneſſes, the two Olive Trees, are.</p>
               <p>Some ſaying they are <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> whom they will have to come. Others ſay, they are <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Ioſua.</hi> And ſome ſay, they are other two men, or more, whom they will have to ſtand up in theſe times. And others ſay, they are the two Churches of the Iewes and Gentiles, and the Miniſters of both. And others, that they are the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſince Chriſt; and ſome ſay, the Magiſtracie and the Miniſtery. And others, the two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments and the Miniſters. And ſome ſay, they are the two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments onely.</p>
               <p>Now which of all theſe opinions is the truth that ſhall ſtand approved when all the reſt ſhall vaniſh like ſmoake, and come to nothing?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:123383:5"/>Surely, not to make any further demurring, the <hi>Two Witneſſes</hi> are the <hi>Two Teſtaments of God,</hi> without the adding or joyning men or Churches unto them, in that reſpect. For which of all thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may be ſaid to empty the pure oyle and light of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and juſtice, grace and truth of God out of themſelves, through their golden pipes, into the golden Candleſtick, which is the Church of God, but his two Teſtaments onely, who have the ſame oyle in themſelves naturally, as the Olive trees have their oyle in themſelves naturally.</p>
               <p>It is true, the Church having received into her ſeven Lamps, of the pure oyle and light of theſe two Olive Trees and two Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes, (as Chriſt alſo calleth them, becauſe they have light in themſelves as well as oyle,) may (through the ſevenfold Spirit of Propheſie given her of God, thoſe ſeven eyes which <hi>Zechariah</hi> ſaw graven on the head Stone, Zech. 3.9. and were with <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> Zech. 4.10. and are the ſeven Spirits of God ſent out into all the earth, ſpoken of alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6.) The Church I ſay, having ſo recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and being made partaker of theſe excellent graces and gifts, may and doth by her Prophets propheſie and hold forth the light of Gods two Witneſſes, the two Olive Trees, and two Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes) and teſtifie the ſame righteouſneſſe and juſtice, grace and truth to the world, in all parts and places where they come. For which cauſe it is ſaid of her, <hi>O Jeruſalem, which bringeſt good tidings, lift up thy voyce with ſtrength, O Sion, that bringeſt good tidings, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe, <hi>How beautifull upon the mountaines are the feet of thoſe that bring good tidings of peace and good things unto us!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of that holy Citie, that ſhe is free, and is the mother of all the children of God, becauſe ſhe miniſters the glad tidings of grace and peace unto them.</p>
               <p>Although all this be true of the Church of God, and that ſhe is ſo neerly united unto his two Witneſſes, as that they cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, nor parted aſunder; yet they may and muſt be diſtinguiſhed ſo one from another, as that the Church and her Prophets may not bee the Witneſſes, nor part of them, nor the Witneſſes the Church: For it can no more be ſo, then the woman mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. which had the two wings given her, (wherewith ſhe might flie into the wildernes) can be the two wings, or the wings the woman; though without them ſhe could not flie, nor be cloathed, nor fed when ſhe was in the wilderneſſe, as the Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, (the two wings being alſo the two Teſtaments) which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123383:6"/>
in them the word of the Lord, wherewith ſhe is in ſpirit cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed and fed, and they are but two, not three, nor foure, nor more, but onely two, which God in thoſe dayes gave unto her (perfectly finiſhed) to be her guide and help every way upon all occaſions, and in all places whereſoever ſhe removed, or ſhould bee diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And therefore Chriſt her Lord, who was carefull of her, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed her beforehand, that then eſpecially, when the time of trouble (which he alſo foretold her of) ſhould come, ſhee ſhould betake herſelfe unto them, as he alſo ſaith, <hi>When yee therefore ſhall ſee the abomination of deſolation ſpoken of by Daniel the Prophet, ſtand in the holy place, who ſo readeth let him underſtand, then let them which be in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea flic into the mountains, &amp;c.</hi> Matth. 24.</p>
               <p>For this was the very time of the great perſecution raiſed by the Dragon againſt that admirable woman in her moſt excellent pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive eſtate, deſcribed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1. whereby ſhe was neceſſitated to flie into the Wilderneſſe to her place which God had provided for her, to take ſome breath and live. She was now to read and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the written words of his two Teſtaments, and to betake her ſelfe to them, and flie (they being the two wings of the great Eagle, even the Lord himſelfe, who gave them unto her to that end; and that ſhe might be alſo nouriſhed by them (in that ſecret deſart) for a time, and times, and half a time, (that is to ſay, three yeares and a halfe of yeares) from the preſence of the Serpent, as verſe 14. compared with verſe 6. where theſe three times and a halfe are decribed by 1260 dayes, and are to be underſtood for ſo many yeares, it being alſo the full time of the reigne of the Beaſt, which was to riſe after the Dragons fall. For St. <hi>Iohn,</hi> as it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, wrote this book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> at the ſame time when all the Weſterne Churches were (by the perſecution of <hi>Nero,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe cruell Pagan Emperours) diſperſed, and they of <hi>Iudea</hi> alſo, <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe being now for the word of God, and witneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, in the Iſle of <hi>Pathmos:</hi> onely the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> remaining in their places undiſperſed, and that this was the reaſon why <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaks not a word of any Churchelſe, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place beſides thoſe ſeven of <hi>Aſia,</hi> unto whom he was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſend the book when he had written it.</p>
               <p>And although (notwithſtanding that great perſecution againſt all Chriſtians in generall then under the Romane power, the name of Chriſt, and profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion, increaſed, ſo that in ſhort time it came to be very generally entertained; yet did the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123383:6"/>
true Church herſelfe (being, in reſpect of her Seed, diſperſed amongſt them) never recover her firſt and primitive eſtate againe; but all things grew worſe and worſe untill the Beaſt roſe, who brought the myſtery of iniquity to perfection, and ſet up the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation to the full, (which the Dragon had begun in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and Temple thereof) to ſtand where it ought not, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Temple of the Chriſtian Gentiles, the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> being now alſo by the Eaſterne Empire, ſubdued to the Beaſt, and brought under the ſupremacie and power of his Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſo they wrought and brought to paſſe by degrees, that the eminent light and beauty of the truly modeſt, and chaſt virgin Spouſe of Chriſt, might no more be ſeen, till the fourty and two months of the Beaſts reigne ſhould be expired.</p>
               <p>Therefore as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>Who ſo readeth, let him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, &amp;c.</hi> So again, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that heare the words of the propheſie of this booke, and keep thoſe things which are written therein, for the time is at hand,</hi> verſe 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 5.</hi>
                     </bibl> And if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth and devoureth their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, ſo muſt he be ſlaine.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre the Lord doth further declare by his Angell, what his two Witneſſes are in their owne true nature and power, in ſaying, <hi>If any man will hurt them, fire ſhall proceed out of their mouth, &amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, if any man ſhall reſiſt their words and teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or ſeem to ſtop their proceeding, and pervert the ſtraight way of the Lord which they declare, as the Scribes and Phariſees, and thoſe falſe teachers in <hi>Antioch,</hi> and them of <hi>Galatia, Elymas</hi> the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer, and many other more in the Apoſtles dayes, did; or ſhall wreſt their words from their true intention, to ſome other falſe and evill ends, and ſo turn their propheſie and teſtimony out of the way, to maintaine their blaſphemous opinions, abominations and lies, under pretence of truth, as <hi>Arius</hi> and his followers did, and the Beaſt and his Clergie have done a long time, and as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe now amongſt us at this day, to maintain their ſundry er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and corrupt opinions; which they have taken up, contrary to the intent and meaning of the Spirit of God in theſe his two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments. Look what judgements they have pronounced againſt ſuch, ſhall ſurely, firſt or laſt, fall upon them, the fire of Gods
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123383:7"/>
juſtice and wrath which proceedeth out of their mouth, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly devoure them.</p>
               <p>And let no man marvell at this, that they being two, are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to have both but one mouth: for although they bee two in number, and are truly diſtinct and differing one from the other, the one being the Law of ſinne, and of death, (ſo called by reaſon of us, who are all guilty of the breach thereof, and ſo of death) which is ſaid to come by <hi>Moſes:</hi> the other being the Law of the Spirit of life, of grace and truth, and is ſaid to come by Jeſus Chriſt; yet doe they not ſpeak or will things contrary one to the other, but doe truly agree and ſpeake as with one mouth that which is holy and juſt, gracious and true. <hi>Therefore if any man will hurt them, ſo muſt he be ſlain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any man ſhall make and love to make lies againſt them, or of them, and ſay they ſpeak that which they ſpeak not, or mean that which they mean not: If any man ſhall adde to, or take from the words of their propheſie, ſee then what their ſentence is, even in the very finiſhing of their teſtimony; If he ſhall adde, God ſhall (then) adde unto him, the plagues that are written in this booke. If he ſhall diminiſh, or take from, God ſhall take away his part out of the book of life, and out of the holy Citie, and from the things that are written in this book, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed</hi> (therefore) <hi>are they that doe his commandements, that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the Citie: for without ſhall be Dogges, and Sorcerers, and Whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and Murderers, and Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſe 6.</hi>
                     </bibl> Theſe have power to ſhut heaven, that it rain not in the dayes of their propheſie; and they have power over the waters, to turn them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to blood, and to ſmite the earth with all manner of plagues ſo often as they will.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THat theſe two Witneſſes have power for to doe all theſe things, I ſuppoſe no man will deny, becauſe it is (without queſtion) true. And that whatſoever they have propheſied againſt any Kingdome, Monarch, Nation, State, Citie, People, for their wickedneſſe againſt their teſtimony, and againſt the Prophets and people of God, that ſtood to maintain the ſame, have and ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come to paſſe. If they propheſie of famine, either of the Word and knowledge of God, which is the bread of life, or of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123383:7"/>
common bread, ſignified here by <hi>ſhutting the heavens that it rain not,</hi> &amp;c. Or if they propheſie of deſtruction by the ſword, here ſignified by <hi>turning waters into blood,</hi> ſo giving them blood to drink for their ſhedding the blood of the Saints, as it is expreſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.3 4.5, 6. Or if they propheſie of peſtilence, of earthquakes, or any other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity or judgement to come, ſignified by <hi>ſmiting the earth with all manner of plagues ſo often as they will,</hi> their word is a law; ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall priviledge and power they have, that what they ſay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, ſhall ſtand, not one jot nor tittle of their word ſhall fail, till all be fulfilled.</p>
               <p>According as the Lord ſpake of his Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and by him ſaying, <hi>Behold, this day have I ſet thee over Nations, and over Kingdomes, to pluck up, root out, deſtroy, and throw down, build and plane, J<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> 1.9, 10. And in another place, <hi>Therefore have I cut them down by my Prophets, and ſlain them by the words of my mouth. Hoſ.</hi> 6.5.</p>
               <p>And ſo <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> (concerning the power that oppoſed him) ſaying, <hi>Not by Army nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts. Who art thou, O great mountain? before Zerubbabel thou ſhalt become a plain, &amp;c.</hi> Zech. 4.</p>
               <p>Now, what two men were there ever in the world, or what two States of Magiſtrates and Miniſters, or other, have there ever been, that had power to doe all theſe things, and by the word of whole mouth, all thoſe judgements of God already paſt and fulfilled on thoſe former Monarchs, Kingdomes, Nations, Cities, people, that have been the great adverſaries of God, enemies to his Word of Truth, and deſtroyers of his Saints, have been uttered and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; but the mouth of his two Teſtaments onely, which the holy Prophets and Apoſtles have been the witneſſers and recorders of. In which reſpect the Lord did ſo greatly honour <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, they being dead, and their writings onely remaining to the people, ſaying, <hi>They have Moſes and the Prophets, let them heare them, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo to us now, we have <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; yea more, we have <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, the <hi>Elias</hi> that was to come, and Chriſt the Meſſiah promiſed, and his holy Apoſtles, (inſomuch as wee have their Records and Writings of the great things of Gods two Teſtaments, which they had ſeen and heard from the Lord.) And if we therefore will not heare them, nor beleeve their record, then neither will we beleeve, if <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> or <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> or any other two or more of the holy Prophets and Apoſtles,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123383:8"/>
ſhould come from the dead, and preach anew unto us: for ſo much doe the words of the Lord imply.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it concerneth us greatly to read and conſider, and to deſire of God to give us underſtanding. And bleſſed is hee that readeth and beleeveth, and keepeth the ſayings of Gods two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which are his two Teſtaments: for ſo I will now take it for granted of all that love the Lord, and delight in his Teſtimonies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 7.</hi>
                     </bibl> And when they have finiſhed their teſtimony, the beaſt which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth from the depth, ſhall make battell againſt them, and kill them.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THeſe words in the opinion of ſome (I know) will ſeeme to contradict that which hath been ſaid of the two Witneſſes, becauſe they will underſtand their teſtimony here ſpoken of, to be their prophecying in Sackcloth 1260 dayes, mentioned in verſe 3. and ſo as if the words of this 7 verſe did imply the killing of them by the Beaſt, to be at the end of thoſe dayes, a little before his own death; that he ſhall then get up again out of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and make warre againſt them, and kill them, and their carkaſſes lie in the ſtreets of his great Citie three naturall yeares and a halfe unburied; that ſo the Beaſt and his falſe Prophets, and thoſe Kings and Nations, and the people that worſhip the Beaſt, may yet rejoyce and triumph over them before the Beaſt die, and his Church come to deſolation.</p>
               <p>This they conceive and teach, and that the two Witneſſes muſt therefore be ſome two men of theſe times, as Mr. <hi>Burton</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſuffered with him, and were impriſoned (as they ſay) three yeares and a halfe juſt to a day; and then ſet at liberty by the Parliament, and ſo raiſed from death to life, and cauſed to ſtand upon their feet again: for ſo they have publiſhed in their bookes: yet not giving the honour wholly to them alone, but joyning alſo together with them all thoſe Miniſters which had ſuffered and been ſuppreſt by the Biſhops, for not conforming unto their orders and rules, who are now reſtored to places and meanes. Some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe, the zealous Magiſtrates and States now in place of authority.</p>
               <p>But to anſwer theſe Teachers, not denying any of Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servants, Magiſtrates or Miniſters, the leaſt part of their due and right; onely let me tell them that ſo teach, They are utterly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123383:8"/>
deceived in their imaginations concerning the two Witneſſes, and alſo much miſtake the words of the text.</p>
               <p>For firſt, it ſaith not of the two Witneſſes (which are the two Teſtaments onely, as hath been ſufficiently proved, and I now take it for granted) And when they have finiſhed their prophecying in Sackcloth, as if they ſhould ceaſe ſo to doe before the Be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſhould kill them. Neither doth it ſay, when the 1260 dayes of the Beaſts reigne ſhall be accompliſhed; then the Beaſt ſhould make warre againſt them, and kill them. Nay, this were very contradictions and unreaſonable: for how could the Beaſt kill them when his dayes were ended? Or if he could, what would it then avail him, the time of their prophecying alſo being expired? Nay, it had been much more for his advantage, to have killed them long before, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were before, even in the Prophet <hi>Zechary</hi> his time, though they had not yet finiſhed their teſtimony till about three hundred yeares before the beaſt roſe.</p>
               <p>And 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, the two Witneſſes of God (being the two Teſtaments) cannot bee ſaid to finiſh their prophecying in Sackcloth, till all Gods elect are called and ſanctified by their word, and that the ſufferings of Chriſt in them his members for his Word ſake, are ended.</p>
               <p>Neither did the two Witneſſes ever otherwiſe propheſie then in Sackcloth, that is, in mourning. All the holy Prophets, Apoſtles and S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ints, have in mourning and weeping born record of them, and in faith and patience teſtified the truth of their words to the world, and were hated and perſecuted for their ſake, not their own; but becauſe they teſtified and walked in the light of them: And in this kind of habit they are to propheſie untill the Lord come in his glory.</p>
               <p>For although the Lord would (as he ſaid) ſo give unto his two Witneſſes, that (notwithſtanding all whatſoever the Beaſt could doe againſt them) they ſhould propheſie the 1260 dayes, even e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of the dayes of thoſe fourty two months of the Beaſts reigne, and the Gentiles treading the holy Citie under foot; yet did he not limit their prophecying in Sackcloth within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of thoſe dayes: Neither is there a word in all the Scripture to ſuch purpoſe; onely their being killed by the Beaſt, and their corps lying dead in the ſtreet of his Sodomiticall Citie, &amp;c. are limited within that time, as we ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ſaid in the Text, the Beaſt which deſcendeth into
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123383:9"/>
the deep, ſhall make warre againſt them, and kill them; but the Beaſt which aſcendeth from the deep, &amp;c. implying plainly, that he ſhould make warre againſt them and kill them at his aſcending or riſing, or ſoone after, and not at his deſcending or downfall. And that the finiſhing their teſtimony here ſpoken of, was to bee before the Beaſt ſhould riſe; which we are here duly to conſider of, as a thing that we ought to know and underſtand. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord foreſhewed, ſaying, <hi>And when they have finiſhed their teſtimony, the Beaſt which aſcendeth from the depth, ſhall make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and kill them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is to ſay, when the holy Prophets, Apoſtles and Evangeliſts had finiſhed their courſe, &amp; written down all whatſoever they had ſeen and heard from the Lord concerning his two Wils &amp; Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according as they were guided by the holy Ghoſt; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his ſecond or laſt Will of grace and peace by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>His wonderfull conception, birth, life, death, reſurrection from the dead, foretold alſo by the Prophets.</p>
               <p>His aſcenſion into heaven, and his ſending the holy Ghoſt unto them, the Spirit of truth to lead them into all truth, and to enable them to propheſie through the ſevenfold gifts thereof.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, who was that <hi>Elias</hi> which God promiſed to ſend before the great and terrible day of the Lord ſhould come, the day of judgement and wrath; and how he cried out unto the people of Iſrael, and ſo unto all the world in the ſpirit and power of <hi>Elias,</hi> requiring every man (with ſtrong perſwaſions, great ſorrowfulneſſe of heart, much lamentation and many teares) to repent, that they might obtaine the forgiveneſſe of their ſinnes through faith in the Meſſiah, the Mediator and Meſſenger of the Covenant, who was now alſo come to his Temple. Which voice of this <hi>Elias</hi> crieth out unto us all, even to this day, that we ſhould repent, that we may receive alſo the forgiveneſſe of our ſinnes by faith in Chriſt, leſt in that great day when he commeth in power and glory, we periſh in his wrath, and he ſmite the earth with a curſe.</p>
               <p>And how Chriſt himſelfe (alſo) preached, ſaving, <hi>Repent, for the Kingdome of heaven is at hand, Repent and beleeve the Goſpel,</hi> with many other heavenly Doctrines, and moſt true and gracious ſayings.</p>
               <p>And of all his wondrous workes, and the things (he had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed them) ſhould come to paſſe. Of the deſtruction of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123383:9"/>
and wrath upon that people. Of falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets that ſhould ariſe. Of great tribulation that ſhould befall the Church of Chriſt during the time of his perſonall abſence. And of the ſignes of his comming, and end of the world.</p>
               <p>And after his death and reſurrection how hee opened their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings; and (among many other heavenly things that he ſpake of; and foreſhewed them) ſaid unto them, <hi>Thus it is written, and thus it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe from the dead the third day, and that repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes ſhould be preached in his Name among all Nations, beginning at Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And then laſt of all, this book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> wherein many great myſteries (that were ſealed up, and no man in heaven nor on earth was found worthy to open, but the Lamb that was ſlain) are by him revealed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The eſtate of his Church in her primitive time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And what her great enemies ſhould be, and what ſhee was to ſuffer at their hands.</p>
               <p>The firſt being the great red Dragon Satan, reigning in the Pagan Emperours; by whoſe bloody perſecutions ſhee was forced to flie into the wilderneſſe to eſcape from his fury, as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.3, 4, 5, 6, &amp;c. deſcribed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.4. by a red horſe, and one fitting on him, that ſhould take peace from the earth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond that of <hi>Arius</hi> and his followers, whoſe blaſphemous doctrines and malicious perſecution againſt thoſe that oppoſed the ſame, continued five months of years, as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.2, 3, 4, 5. deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by a black horſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.5.</p>
               <p>The third, this of the Beaſt and his falſe prophets, and whoriſh Church; of whoſe abominations and filthineſſes of the cup of her fornications, Kings, Princes, and people of all Nations, have been made to drink, and became drunken, committing fornication with her, and ſo their ſouls became loſt for ever.</p>
               <p>And her ſelfe alſo becomming daily drunken with the blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe bodies ſhe killed, becauſe they would not drink of her cup, nor commit fornication with her. All which being to continue fourty and two months of years, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.5. deſcribed alſo in <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. by a pale horſe, &amp;c. ver. 8.</p>
               <p>Then what plagues ſhould bee powred out upon them all for their murders and wickedneſſe. And what and when ſhould bee their end, and how great their condemnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:123383:10"/>And which exceeds all (for the comfort of the Church of Chriſt, which was to ſuffer all theſe things at her enemies hands) how ſhee ſhould bee delivered from her ſo great and violent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
               <p>And what and how great things her Lord hath prepared for her, and promiſed and foreſhewed her, eſpecially in this booke of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> to be inherited of her for eternity in the world to come, when he ſhall appeare in his glory.</p>
               <p>So, the holy Prophets, and Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts, having from the Lord perfected his two Teſtaments (which are his two Witneſſes) they having thus finiſhed their teſtimony, which was never to done before, nor (from thence forth) could ever bee ſo done after; and, which might therefore rightly be called, <hi>Finiſhing their Teſtimony:</hi> and alſo, becauſe no man, nor Angel from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, might or may preach any thing as the teſtimony of Gods two Witneſſes, or his Oracles, but what is written and contained in them, it being the whole counſell of God.</p>
               <p>So I ſay, they having thus finiſhed their teſtimony, and they being prophecying in the plain demonſtration of the Spirit and of power, turning the hearts of Gods elect to repentance, that they might be juſtified from their ſinnes by faith through his grace in Chriſt, which by the Spirit, and word of reconciliation, was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to their broken and contrite hearts: And alſo by the ſame Spirit and power convincing the wicked periſhing world of ſinne, of righteouſneſſe, and of judgement.</p>
               <p>Of judgement, becauſe the prince of this world, whom they ſerve and obey (he ruling in their hearts) is judged already.</p>
               <p>So thoſe dwellers on earth, being tormented with their juſt and righteous ſayings, which the Saints and ſervants of God, the true ſucceſſors of the holy Apoſtles and Church of their time maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt their ungodly, ſuperſtitious, filthy, fleſh-pleaſing wayes. And the beaſt, hee being now riſen up and ſeated in the Dragons Throne; and there being nothing more tormenting or grievous unto him and his falſe prophets, and thoſe dwellers on earth, then the true and righteous doctrines and prophecies of theſe two Prophets, Gods anointed ones, the light whereof being ſo contrary to their wayes and works.</p>
               <p>Therfore as holding it their wiſeſt &amp; ſureſt way, that they ſhould torment them no longer, they make battell againſt them, and kill them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:123383:10"/>And this they effected and brought to paſſe, partly by belying their teſtimony, giving moſt falſe and blaſphemous expoſitions of their ſayings, making the world beleeve that ſo they meant; and partly by ſuppreſſing thoſe which ſtood to maintain their true intent and meaning; and partly by keeping cloſe their written words, forbidding them to bee publiſhed or read in any of the tongues or languages of the Nations, which were under the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power of the beaſt, that the people ſhould not come to the knowledge and underſtanding of them, leſt they ſhould ſee and diſcover their falſe and deceitfull deluſions.</p>
               <p>So the beaſt and his falſe prophets, by putting out the light and true intent of Gods two Witneſſes (which was and is their life) they killed them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 8.</hi>
                     </bibl> And their carkaſſes ſhall remaine in the ſtreets of the great Citie, which is ſpiritually called Sodome and Egypt; where alſo their Lord was crucified.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ONely their dead letter, or bare text of their teſtimony, they would retaine and keep, as wee ſee they have done in their Cells, Temples, and ſtreets of the Nations and Kingdomes where the beaſt is worſhipped, who with <hi>Rome</hi> their chiefe, doe make up that great Citie; which becauſe of their ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and hardneſſe of heart, are deſcribed by the names of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> they anſwering in a ſpirituall manner unto them both.</p>
               <p>And they are charged alſo with the crucifying of the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, (even as the Lord had charged the Scribes and Phariſees of his time with the blood of <hi>Abel</hi>) becauſe, like as they imitated <hi>Cain</hi> in hardneſſe of heart and wickedneſſe, in their killing the Prophets, as he did his brother: So theſe, imitating thoſe of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> that crucified the Lord of life, in their murdering his faithful Servants, his Saints &amp; Martyrs, are juſtly charged with cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying the Lord; they making up one generation with all the Heathen and wicked murderers, and ſhedders of righteous blood in the world. For which cauſe he ſaith, <hi>And in her was found the blood of Prophets, and of Saints, and of all that were ſlaine upon the earth, Rev.</hi> 18.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:123383:11"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 9.</hi>
                     </bibl> And there ſhall of the Tribes, and People, and Gentiles, ſee their dead bodies, three dayes and a halfe, and ſhall not ſuffer their Corps to be laid in Monuments.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd ſo, thoſe Nations and Kingdomes, People and Gentiles, under the name of Catholick Chriſtians, having the dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or letter of Gods two Witneſſes lying in their ſtreets, could, and can yet handle and look upon them, while thoſe three dayes and a halfe, the time, times, and halfe a time of the beaſts reigne laſteth: That is to ſay, (not as the beaſt, and they of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> expound it) three naturall yeares and a halfe, which they will have to be the time of the reigne of a great Antichriſt of their imagining, (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they pretend is yet to come) but 3 propheticall years &amp; a halfe: that is, ſo many years of years, which (according to the account of the Hebrews, are, 1260 years. A long time for Gods two Teſtaments to lie dead among them, and not ſuffered to be ſo read, or heard, as they maybe underſtood and laid up in the hearts of the people, where they ought to have been laid and kept, as in their true and naturall graves or tombs, where they ſhould have been buried, not to be forgotten, but to be kept in memoriall to the praiſe of God, and ſalvation of his people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 10.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the inhabitants of the earth ſhall bee glad over them, and ſhall ſend gifts one to another; becauſe theſe two Prophets tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them that dwell upon the earth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NOw the beaſt &amp; his falſe prophets, and all thoſe worſhippers of the beaſt here named, (becauſe of their great number) <hi>The Inhabitants of the earth:</hi> they having attained their wills, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed over Gods two Witneſſes, and caſt his truth to the ground, (as the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo foretold) are glad at their hearts; and, in triumph over them, and for joy that they may now goe on qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, in ſetting up and adoring their own inventions. They (as one well obſerveth) make themſelves merry with bonfires, vigils, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals, proceſſions, and in token of their joy (as the text ſaith) <hi>ſend gifts one to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Kings, Princes and people preſent and endow the beaſt and his Church, with donations, immunities, poſſeſſions, gold and ſilver offerings, &amp;c. And the beaſt on the other ſide requites their love
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123383:11"/>
and devotion with Titles, Bells, Prayers, Pardons, Bulls, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon of this their wicked and ungodly rejoycing, is, becauſe they had put out the eyes or light of Gods two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are here named two Prophets, and (before) his two Witneſſes, and two Olive Trees, and two Candleſticks, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4.) that their abominations &amp; filthineſſes of their fornications, might not be diſcovered and reproved by them, as formerly had been, which was ſo tormenting unto them, and is, and will be ſtill, to all ſuch lovers and beleevers of lies, (whoſe hope and converſation, and dwelling, is here on earth) as nothing can be more.</p>
               <p>For ſo much doe the words imply in ſaying, <hi>Becauſe theſe two Prophets tormented them that dwell upon the earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 11.</hi>
                     </bibl> And after three dayes and a halfe the Spirit of life from God entred into them, and they ſtood upon their feet, and great feare fell upon all that ſaw them.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd after three dayes and a halfe (that is to ſay) <hi>after the time and times, and halfe a time</hi> of the Beaſts reigne, ſpoken of in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25, &amp; 12.7. and mentioned in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14. to be the time of the woman being nouriſhed in the wilderneſſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo, taking a day in this place, as a time is to bee taken in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14. Then theſe three dayes and a halfe, in a propheticall underſtanding, are (as the three times and a halfe are) three yeares and a halfe of yeares.</p>
               <p>And therefore, not as they of <hi>Rome</hi> would have them, three na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall yeares and a halfe, which they make to bee the time of their expected two witneſſes <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> and their being killed, and lying dead, &amp;c. and of their Churches deſolation, and being in the wilderneſſe, which they pretend they expect ſhall come to paſſe upon the riſing of their Antichriſt, (a Jew of the Tribe of <hi>Dan</hi>) and by him who is to be borne they know not where nor when, and yet muſt reigne thoſe three years and a halfe, and doe all theſe things.</p>
               <p>Neither can any of thoſe among our ſelves, which are ſo neere of opinion unto them of <hi>Rome,</hi> (concerning the three dayes and a halfe, of the two Witneſſes being ſlain) ſhew any one ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why a propheticall yeare may not be intended in this place by the name of a day, as well as by the name of a time in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123383:12"/>
and 12.7. and Rev. 12.14. which I ſuppoſe they acknowledge.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing alſo that a day is a time as well and truly as an houre is a time, or a month, or a yeare. Vnder all which termes the time of the reigne of the great Antichriſt is expreſt, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10. &amp; 9.13, 14, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Where <hi>John</hi> (having ſeen their great and terrible Army of horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and heard alſo the number of them to bee twenty thouſand times ten thouſand) deſcribeth them alſo to have breaſt-plates of fire, and of Jacinth, and of brimſtone, and their horſes to have heads, as the heads of Lions: and that out of their mouthes iſſued fire and ſmoke, and brimſtone, and having tailes like Serpents, with heads on them. And that all theſe (whoſe power is in their mouthes, and in their tailes) were prepared for an houre, and a day, and a month, and a yeare, to ſlay the third part of men, <hi>verſe</hi> 15, 16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p>This is that laſt houre ſpoken of in 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. The houre of temptation, which was to come upon all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p>So then if an houre may contain ſo long a time, why not a day? if a day, then why not three dayes and a half as well as three times and a halfe, ſeeing three dayes and a halfe are three times and a halfe?</p>
               <p>Neither is it poſſible that all thoſe things which are to be done within the time of the two Witneſſes lying dead and unburied in the ſtreets of that great Citie, ſhould bee fulfilled and done in ſo ſhort a time as three naturall yeares and a halfe.</p>
               <p>That the Beaſt and his falſe prophets (that great Army of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting horſemen) with all thoſe Kings, Princes, and Tribes, and people, and Gentiles, and inhabitants of the earth, which worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, ſhould ſo univerſally, &amp; ſo publickly in all places make thoſe merriments with bonfires, feſtivals, wakes, &amp;c. rejoycing over their own inventions, (and for that they had put out the light of the truth of Gods two Witneſſes which ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them in their ways) and ſend ſuch great gifts alſo one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for joy thereof, chopping and changing, &amp; making Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of all things, even of the very ſouls of men, as it is declared, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.12, 13. and as experience hath ſufficiently proved they have done, no ſhort time ſlaying and deſtroying with their inchantments and ſorceries (the fire, and ſmoke, and brimſtone, which iſſued out of the mouthes of thoſe monſtrous horſemen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123383:12"/>
and their horſes, and the mouthes of their tailes) the ſouls of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand men, of all degrees, high and low, and of all nations, even a full third part of the world; and yet the reſt that were not ſlain by theſe plagues, repented not of their workes, that they ſhould not worſhip Divels, and Idols of gold and ſilver, and braſſe, and ſtone, and wood, which neither can ſee, nor heare, nor walke, nor repent of their murders, nor of their ſorceries, nor of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, nor of their theſis.</p>
               <p>I ſay it is not poſſible that all theſe things (which are to be done while the two Witneſſes lie ſlain in the ſtreets) ſhould be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in three common yeares and a halfe, but muſt have the full time of the Beaſts reigne for the ſam; the time of thoſe Gentiles treading the holy Citie under foot, and of the woman being fed in the wilderneſſe even 1260. yeares.</p>
               <p>After which (as the text ſaith) the Spirit of life from God ſhall enter into his two Prophets, and they ſhall ſtand upon their feet, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>God will then, in, and about that time eſpecially, raiſe up faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Scribes indeed, and Shepheards of underſtanding hearts, whom he will teach and inſtruct in the wayes of his truth; and give them ſo to underſtand the words and teſtimonies of his two Witneſſes, as that they ſhall through the power of his grace, declare the true intent and meaning of them, and ſet forth and divide the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people: (Like unto the good houſholder, or as the Scribe taught in the Kingdome of God, that is alwayes provided of things both new and old, and is ready to miniſter upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in, and at all due times and ſeaſons, according to the words of Chriſt, and as <hi>Paul</hi> once charged <hi>Timothy</hi>) that they alſo may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, and walk in the light thereof to the praiſe of God, and their own ſalvation.</p>
               <p>And ſo, the true ſpirituall and heavenly meaning of Gods two Teſtaments, their light and life, (which their enemies had taken away, and kept out of fight and knowledge ſo long, being now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored) they his two Prophets walk upon their feet againe, as well to the terror and aſtoniſhment of all falſe and lying interpreters, as to the reverend feare, admiration and comfort of all the children and juſtifiers of wiſdome; for ſo much do the words imply, <hi>And great feare fell upon all that ſaw them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if any man ſhall marvell how the two Witneſſes may bee ſaid to propheſie all the time of the reigne of the Beaſt, and their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123383:13"/>
bodies lie dead in the ſtreets of his Sodomiticall Citie all the while, let him conſider, that although they lie dead in his ſtreets, yet they ſpeake and propheſie notwithſtanding, like as did the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> and the bones of <hi>Eliſha.</hi> And whatſoever they have ſpoken or propheſied in the written words of their Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, either againſt the Beaſt and his Church, and all other falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers and beliers of them: or as concerning their owne reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the good of the Church and children of God, ſhall ſurely come to paſſe and be fulfilled, let the Beaſt and all the reſt of them doe what they can.</p>
               <p>Neither doe nor did their bodies lie dead and unburied among the Saints, and children of the woman that fled into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they have been living and propheſying with them all this while, and their enemies have heard their voyce from thence many and ſundry times ſounding in their eares, though they hardened their hearts againſt it, and ſought ſtill by their cunning inquiſitions to lay hold of, ſhut up in their dungeons, and ſlay all thoſe that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl> And I heard a lowd voyce from Heaven, ſaying, Come up hither, and they went up to heaven in a cloud, and their enemies ſaw them.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NOw the true meaning of the Scriptures contained in the two Teſtaments of God, which had been ſo long obſcured by falſe and lying expoſiters, ſhall be ſo famouſly publiſhed and made known, and by ſuch plain demonſtration of the Spirit and power of God, as that no power of wickedneſſe whatſoever ſhall any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bee able to ſtop or hinder the glorious courſe and proſperous proceeding therof: but that (as one well obſerveth from the words, <hi>And I heard a lowd voyce from heaven, ſaying, Come up hither</hi>) it ſhould be more poſſible for them to ſtay <hi>Elias</hi> Chariot from aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, or to pull the wind back from purſuing his poynt, then to reſiſt the power and wiſdome of the ſame, which ſhall vindicate the abuſe of the Scriptures, and by the ſame Spirit and power of God in the miniſtery of his faithfull ſervants (as in the ſtrength of cloud) ſhall hold them up, and reſtore them to their ſpirituall and heavenly meaning again: And ſo as the beaſt with his falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Sorcerers and liers, (which have been their long and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient enemies) ſhall ſee the glory of their reſtauration, and wonder
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123383:13"/>
thereat and die: for ſo much doe the words imply in ſaying, <hi>And they went up to heaven in a cloud, and their enemies ſaw them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 13.</hi>
                     </bibl> And in that houre there was made a great earthquake, and the tenth part of the Citie fell, and there were ſlain in the earthquake names of men ſeven thouſand, and the reſt were eaſt into a feare, and gave glory to the God of heaven.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd in the ſame houre (ſaith the Spirit of God) <hi>there was made a great earthquake:</hi> As much as to ſay, In the ſame very time when it ſhould pleaſe God to begin his work of raiſing up and reſtoring his two Witneſſes to life and ſtrength again (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is declared) there ſhould be made a great diſturbance in the Chriſtian world (where the Beaſt ſhould reigne) concerning mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion: And that a tenth part of the Citie, that is, of the ſame Chriſtian world or State where the Beaſt is worſhipped, ſhould fall from the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>And that in this great earthquake and diſturbance, and fall of the tenth part of the Citie, there ſhould bee ſlain many thouſand men, ſignified here by <hi>names of men ſeven thouſand,</hi> for ſtanding up to maintain the true doctrine of Gods two Teſtaments againſt the Beaſt, and his abominations and lies; and becauſe they would not worſhip him nor his image any longer.</p>
               <p>And that the reſt (meaning thoſe that were in their conſciences reproved, and in their minds enlightned by the evident light of the truth ſo witneſſed) <hi>were caſt into a feare, &amp;c.</hi> that is, into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend feare and admiration, and gave glory to the God of heaven, praiſed his name, and uſed all meanes both by word and deed to eſtabliſh and ſupport the ſame doctrine of truth, that it might bee yet more publickly knowne to the world. The words implying, that among theſe reſt ſo enlightned, which gave glory to the God of heaven, ſome were Princes and Rulers of the people and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who had civill power alſo to promote this great worke, and made uſe thereof accordingly.</p>
               <p>And the houre or time in the which this great earthquake ſhould be made, and worke of reformation begin, was (as it muſt needs be underſtood and acknowledged) that very time when thoſe great troubles, broyles and bloodſheddings were in <hi>Bohemia, Germany, France, Flanders,</hi> &amp; others parts, as alſo in <hi>England,</hi> for and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the inſtitution of religion, whereof hiſtories doe ſo clearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:123383:14"/>Whereupon (as we have ſeen, and doe ſee by experience) ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Kingdomes and States of Chriſtendome (a tenth part at leaſt) that were under the power and ſubjection of the Beaſt, have fallen from him, and forſaken his abominations, and have ſet their help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hands to the building of the walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to reſtore the morning and evening Sacrifice of praiſe and thankeſgiving to God in ſome part and meaſure anſwerable to that which was once in the former time, and in the dayes of old. And ſo it is true, a tenth part of the Citie fell and is fallen.</p>
               <p>For we are to underſtand, that although the reſurrection of the two Witneſſes, or reſtitution of the true meaning of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is not yet perfected, nor ſo known and underſtood (in every part) and publiſhed, as God will have it to be in this laſt age of the world; nor the woman, his true Church, come fully forth of the the Wilderneſſe, nor ſhall till after the three dayes and a halfe of the beaſts reigne, mentioned in verſe 11. yet the beginning of both was to be before, and their light and brightneſſe have increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ever ſince to this day, and ſhall yet ſtill more and more daily, even as Antichriſt and his Church with her abominations, conſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth daily.</p>
               <p>For like as the beaſt and his Church, with that myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, came not to perfection at once, but by degrees, according as they could, and did by degrees put out the light of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and extinguiſh the beauty and face of the true Church of Chriſt (the life of the one depending (as it were) upon the death of the other.) So on the contrary part, it is and ſhall be now, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (with the Spirit of his mouth) is to conſume the beaſt by degrees, his two Witneſſes are to ſtand upon their feet, and his Church is to appeare out of the wilderneſſe in part and meaſure ſometime before the end of the beaſt, that they may by the truth of their teſtimony, diſcover him and his abominations openly to the world, that ſo thoſe ten hornes, or Kings, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes which formerly gave themſelves and their power unto the beaſt, might by degrees alſo, ſome after other, fall from him, and come to hate the whore with her filthineſſes, &amp; to devour her fleſh by the Sword, and burn her with fire, according to the word of the Lord, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6. And that alſo (for Gods elect ſake) thoſe daies (in reſpect of the evils and great tribulation of them) might now even while the beaſt yet remaineth in his throne, be ſhortned, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as Chriſt foretold, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:123383:14"/>Therefore let not now any of Gods choſen be diſmayed at any thing they ſhall heare of or ſee, though in their preſent appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions never ſo contrary, but let them know there can nothing prevent God of his purpoſe, nor hinder or put by the fulfilling of any part of his word; what hee hath ſpoken ſhall ſtand, let the beaſt, and all the powers of wickedneſſe in the world with him, do what they can, the truth ſhall certainly proſper, and the beaſt with all his power the Dragon beſtowed upon him, of what kind ſoever, ſhall prevail no longer.</p>
               <p>For who art thou, O great mountain <hi>Babel,</hi> the perfection and full accompliſhment of all the former <hi>Babels</hi> and mountains of confuſion that have been in the world? And what art thou before him that fitteth on the white horſe, whoſe name is called, <hi>The Word of God?</hi> He with the ſharp ſword that proceedeth out of his mouth, ſhall not only go on to conſume thee even to the laſt hour of thy dayes determined, but ſhall alſo take thee and thy falſe prophets, thoſe two hundred thouſand thouſand Clergymen, that wrought miracles before thee, and caſt yee both alive into the lake of fire, burning with brimſtone, according as it is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.</p>
               <p>And then ſhall his two Witneſſes prophecie in their full ſtrength more publickly and freely then yet they doe, and his Church come fully forth of the wilderneſſe, that her modeſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, her holy and heavenly converſation, may be more clearly ſeen then yet is or hath been for theſe many hundred yeares paſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 14.</hi>
                     </bibl> The ſecond woe is gone, and behold the third woe will come quickly.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN Chap. 8. mention is made of three woes that were to come upon the world, and be within the time of the ſounding of the three laſt of the 7 Trumpets which the 7 Angels were to ſound, <hi>v.</hi> 13. where <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>And I beheld and heard an Angel flying through the middeſt of heaven, ſaying with a lowd voyce, Woe, woe, woe to the inhabitants of the earth, by reaſon of the other voyces of the Trumpets of the three Angels which are yet to ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe three woes being that of <hi>Arianiſme</hi> before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which is deſcribed in Chap. 9. from ver. 1. to ver. 11. and is ſaid to continue five months, ver. 5. meaning in the propheticall underſtanding, months of years, which according to the Hebrews account, who had thirty dayes to every month, and twelve months
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123383:15"/>
to every year) doe containe the juſt number of an hundred and fifty years, which was the time of the <hi>Arian</hi> perſecution, and prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of that hereſie, as Hiſtories doe plainly report.</p>
               <p>This, and no other thing, can rightly be taken for the firſt <hi>Woe;</hi> neither may the perſons or workers thereof, be thought to bee Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens, Arabians, Mahometans, as ſome name them and would have them, nor any other heathen powers or people without the outer Court or Pale of the Church: but Chriſtians by profeſſion, and ſuch as had great place and power in the outward ſtate of the Church, wherby to worke their miſchievous <hi>Woe</hi> in ſtinging and poiſoning the inhabitants of the earth with their helliſh ſmoky blaſphemous doctrine, and to perſecute the Saints of God that oppoſed the ſame.</p>
               <p>The holy Ghoſt having from the firſt verſe of this ninth chapter, to the eleventh verſe, made a full deſcription of this firſt <hi>Woe,</hi> it being the leaſt of the three, and no more again to bee mentioned, ſaith here, ver. 12. <hi>One woe is paſt.</hi> And becauſe each of the other two would be farre greater, he ſaith, <hi>And behold</hi> (as requiring all men to hearken and take ſpeciall notice of it) <hi>two woes more come hereafter.</hi> And then preſently following, ſaith, ver. 13. <hi>And the ſixth Angel ſounded, &amp;c.</hi> From which to the end of the Chapter, in a very brief and generall manner, is foreſhewed not onely the frightfull uglineſſe, and monſtrous deformed ſhapes of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſhould work this ſecond <hi>Woe,</hi> and cauſe that abominable myſtery of iniquity to overſpread the earth, and how great the number of their Army of Horſmen ſhould be; but alſo with what Devilliſh weapons of helliſh fire, ſmoke, and brimſtone, iſſuing forth of their mouthes and tailes, they ſhould effect it, to the ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the the third part of men.</p>
               <p>Which ſtrangely deformed great Army, are not nor may bee thought to bee that of the Turkes, which have invaded, and doe now poſſeſſe a part of Europe, as ſome conceive and publiſh. Nay, but they are Chriſtians alſo by profeſſion, as were the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the firſt woe, even the whole race and generation of the great Antichriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> and legions of his falſe prophets. Theſe are the true authors and workers of this ſecond <hi>Woe;</hi> who now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhew themſelves in their faſhion when the ſixth Angel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſound, v. 13, 14.</p>
               <p>And ſo in reſpect of that firſt <hi>Woe</hi> of <hi>Arianiſme,</hi> which began with the ſounding of the fifth Angels Trumpet, and continued
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:123383:15"/>
five months: This of Antichriſt, which was to begin with the ſounding of the ſixth Angels Trumpet, and to continue fourty and two months, is in Chap. 11.4. called, <hi>The ſecond Woe.</hi> Which <hi>woe</hi> although it was to be, and is more particularly, and much more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly and largely diſcovered in Chapters 13. and 14. and Chap. 17. and 18. and 19. yet becauſe it is here in Chap. 11. in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall manner fully revealed, the Lord (to whom all things paſt and to come are preſent) ſaith verſ. 14. <hi>The ſecond woe is gone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe the third woe is to come very ſoon after, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt of all, he ſaith again, <hi>And behold,</hi> calling unto (as it were) and requiring all men to hearken and conſider of it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And behold, the third woe will come;</hi> meaning the great day of the Lords comming in his glory to judge the world, which will bee a day of terror unto all thoſe inhabitants of the earth that repented not of their ſinnes, and ſorceries, and murders, &amp;c. that beleeved not in him, and of the greateſt woe to them that ever came.</p>
               <p>For all the woes as they are woes, doe belong to the ungodly, and are ſo called in reſpect of them, not of the juſt; neither will the day of the Lords coming in glory, be a day of terror or woe to them; but rather on the clean contrary, the day of their greateſt joy, the day which they looked for.</p>
               <p>And that they his choſen and faithfull, ſhould know and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand upon certainty, that this great day of the Lord ſhall not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long, but come ſoon after the deſolation of Antichriſt, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this word quickly, <hi>And behold the third woe will come quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which very thing the Lord alſo confirmed before in another place, by the like word, <hi>immediatly, Matth.</hi> 24. where hee having ſpoken of the tyrannous reign of the ſelfe-ſame Antichriſt, and his falſe prophets, verſe 23, 24. ſaith, <hi>Immediatly after the tribulation of thoſe dayes, ſhall the Sunne be darkned, and the Moon ſhall not give her light, and the Starres ſhall fall from heaven, and the powers of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall be ſhaken, and then ſhall appeare the ſigne of the Sonne of Man in heaven, and then ſhall all the Tribes of the earth mourne, and they ſhall ſee the Sonne of man comming in the clouds of heaven, with power and great glory, and he ſhall ſend his Angels with a great found of a Trumpet, &amp;c verſe</hi> 29.13.31.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the length of the time that is to bee between the end of Antichriſt and the day of the Lords comming in glory, intended by the word <hi>quickly,</hi> and the word <hi>immediatly.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel</hi> (ſpeaking likewiſe of the reigne of the ſame Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123383:16"/>
and number of his dayes, as alſo of the end of the world, which is to be at the day of the Lords comming) declareth it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to contain fourty and five yeares, according to the Chaldees ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. his words being theſe; <hi>And from the time that the daily Sacrifice ſhall be taken away, and the abomination that maketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, ſet up, there ſhall bee a thouſand two hundred and ninety dayes. Bleſſed is he that wayteth, and commeth to the thouſand three hundred and five and thirty dayes;</hi> (adding to the thouſand two hundred and ninety dayes, five and thirty dayes more, which make a thouſand three hundred thirty five) and then ſaith (as being the words of the Angel of God to <hi>Daniel) But go thou thy way till the end be, for thou ſhalt reſt and ſtand up in the lot at the end of the dayes, verſ.</hi> 11, 12, 13. The Prophet (from the Angel) intending by dayes, yeares, and counting the years after the uſe of the Chaldeans, and not of the Hebrewes, between whom (in three years and a halfe, there was as it ſeemeth, thirty dayes difference.</p>
               <p>And ſo, if <hi>Daniel</hi> was to goe his way and reſt till the and bee, and that he ſhall ſtand up in the lot at the end of the dayes, then muſt the end of neceſſity be at the end of the dayes. But <hi>Daniel</hi> was to goe his way till the end ſhould be, and was to reſt, and ſtand in the lot at the end of the dayes; therefore the end of the dayes muſt needs be the end, even the end of the world.</p>
               <p>And now therefore, if the time between the end of thoſe dayes of Antichriſts reigne, and the end of the world, will indeed for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain be ſo ſhort as thoſe Scriptures declare, then where will there be time or place for that glorious thouſand yeares Monarch of Saints, which ſo many learned Miniſters and zealous people at this day look for, and hold as an Article of their faith, to bee here in this preſent world, before the end thereof? Surely, neither the Prophets, nor Chriſt, nor any of his Apoſtles, doe admit of ſuch a thing.</p>
               <p>Thoſe people and Miniſters whatſoever they are for zeale and learning, they are herein utterly deceived, miſunderſtanding the Scriptures, which ſpeak indeed of a glorious Kingdome, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great and excellent things the Saints ſhall receive and poſſeſſe, not for the limited time of a thouſand yeares in this corrupt world, but for ever and ever, a thouſand and ten thouſand times ten thouſand yeares, even for eternity in the uncorrupt world to come, which world and kingdome ſhall have no end, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.7. <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.14, 15, 16 <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14.25. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.32,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123383:16"/>
33. and ſundry other places. Thoſe Miniſters and people therefore w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> look for ſuch a millenary Monarchical kingdom in this world, may do well to renounce that Atticle of their faith, as they call it, &amp; in meeknes and humblenes of heart ſeek and deſire of God, to give them his holy Spirit of truth, whereby to underſtand with comfort his word of truth.</p>
               <p>The things that are to be between the end of Antichriſts reigne, and the end of the world, are by Chriſt himſelfe foreſhewed in theſe words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>Immediatly after the tribulation of thoſe dayes, ſhall the Sunne be darkned, and the Moone ſhall not give her light, and the Starres ſhall fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens ſhall bee ſhaken, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the Lord intendeth by the Sunne, the word of his truth, the Goſpel of ſalvation, which had been darkned by Antichriſt, and ſhould now toward the end of his dayes, break forth and ſhine again, to diſcover his abominations, and for the ſaving of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, (which the Lord alſo intended before, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. in theſe words, <hi>But for the elect ſake thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned.</hi>) And implying alſo that it ſhould ſhine yet more brightly after the end of Antichriſt, and that the greateſt part of the time of 45 yeares, intended by the word <hi>quickly,</hi> and the word <hi>immediatly,</hi> ſhall be for the proſperous proceeding of the Goſpel, and full accompliſhing of all Gods elect.</p>
               <p>And as the Sunne thus ſhineth, ſo ſhall the Moon, that is to ſay, the earth, and the inhabitants thereof, whoſe light doth depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the light of the Goſpel, as the light of the Moon doth on the light of the Sunne, ſhe ſhall now give her light, according alſo as a holy one in another place ſaith, <hi>The Sun ſhall ſuddenly ſhine again in the night, and the Moon three times in the day, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Starres of God ſhall appeare in heaven, God will raiſe up in his Church true and faithfull Shepheards, that ſhall as ſtarres in heaven hold forth the light and truth of his two Teſtaments to the word, and ſo the powers of the heavens ſpirituall, will bee in their heavenly way and order again.</p>
               <p>All theſe things are plainly implied in the words of Chriſt, elſe how can the Sunne be ſaid to be darkned, and the Moon to loſe her light, and the Starres to fall from heaven, &amp;c. immediatly after the tribulation of thoſe dayes of Antichriſt, if they did not, and ſhould not ſhine forth and give their light ſome time before the end of thoſe dayes, and alſo after, more eſpecially, therefore all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123383:17"/>
theſe things muſt be. And the true Church of Chriſt which had been troden under foot, and cauſed to hide her face, as it were, in the wilderneſſe ſo long, ſhall come forth and bee ſeene neer like as ſhe was once in her primitive ſtate, clothed with the Sunne, even Jeſus Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe; and having the Moon, that is, all earthly and corruptible things under her feet, as diſregarded, her converſation and affections being farre above them all, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where her Lord is, and from whence ſhee looketh for him to come, and bring all thoſe his rewards with him that hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: And having alſo on her head a Crown of twelve ſtarres, the true and ſound doctrine of the Lambs twelve Apoſtles, and of the holy Prophets, walking in the light and truth thereof, according as they walked with true love toward God, and alſo toward men. And ſo be, as once ſhe was (in theſe ſpirituall &amp; heavenly reſpects) truely viſible, like a Citie ſet upon a hill, that cannot be hid; and as a Candle in a Candleſtick which giveth light to all in the houſe, her faith ſhining again throughout the world.</p>
               <p>And when ſhee ſhall bee in this eſtate (like as at the firſt) when ſhe was travelling with child to bring forth her firſt fruits unto God and to the Lamb, the Dragon ſtood before her to devoure her child, and perſecute the woman into the wilderneſſe, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>So now, when ſhe ſhall be travelling with child again, ready to bring forth her laſt fruits unto God and to Chriſt, then the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, that old Serpent, being looſed out of his priſon (where he had been bound ſo many hundred yeares) ſhall goe out to deceive the Nations that are in the four quarters of the earth, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and gather them together, and compaſſe the camp of the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and this the beloved Citie, till fire deſcend from God out of heaven and devoure them, as it is written, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. and 39. Rev. 16.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9.</p>
               <p>For as the time of the Churches faireſt beauty was but ſhort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Dragon ſo cruelly uſed her: ſo ſhall this time of her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed beauty be as ſhort before he ſhall be looſed to work this his laſt miſehiefe againſt her.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall the Sunne be darkned more then ever it had been, it ſhall be as black as Sackcloth of haire, and the Moon ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be darkned, but alſo be turned into blood, as it is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12. according to <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.31. For great bloodſhed ſhall be upon the earth at this time as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> alſo ſaith.</p>
               <p>And the Starres, that is, ſuch as are in outward place and name,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123383:17"/>
as ſtarres and lights in the Church, ſhall like untimely figges, fall from Chriſtian religion to Mahometiſme, or other ſuch like hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Apoſtaſie, and then ſhall the powers of the Heavens bee ſhaken.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſignes that ſhall goe before the great and terrible day of the Lord, as thoſe Scriptures before mentioned declare.</p>
               <p>And then thoſe Armies of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> being deſtroyed by fire from heaven, and the Devill that deceived them being caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lake of fire, the ſeventh Angell ſhall ſound the great and laſt trumpet, as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Verſ. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the ſeventh Angel ſounded with a Trumpet, and there were made lowd voyces in heaven, ſaying, The Kingdomes of this world are made our Lords, and his Chriſts, and hee ſhall reigne for ever and ever. Amen.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MAny great things are to bee done at the ſounding of this Trumpet: For this is it of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We which are alive, and remain unto the comming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them that are aſleep, for the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from heaven with a ſhout, with the voyce of the Archangel, &amp; with the Trump of God, and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt; then we which are are alive and remain, ſhall bee caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the aire, and ſo ſhall we be even with the Lord,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>Behold, I ſhew you a myſtery, we ſhall not all ſleep, but wee ſhall all be changed, in a moment, in the twinckling of an eye, at the laſt trump: for the trumpet ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, and we ſhall be changed, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.51, 52, 53.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt ſaith, Mat. 24. <hi>Then ſhall appeare the ſigne of the Son of man in heaven, and then ſhall all the Tribes of the earth mourn, and they ſhall ſee the Sonne of Man comming in the clouds of heaven with power and great glory, and he ſhall ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet, and they ſhall gather together his elect from the foure winds, &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 30, 31.</p>
               <p>And again, Rev. 10. <hi>And the Angel which I ſaw ſtand upon the Sea, and upon the earth, lifted up his hand to heaven, and ſware by him that liveth for ever and ever, who created heaven, and the things that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are, and the earth, and the things that therein are, and the ſea and the things that are therein, that there ſhould be time no longer. But in the dayes of the voyce of the ſeventh Angel, when he ſhall begin to ſound, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123383:18"/>
myſtery of God ſhould be finiſhed, as he hath declared to his ſervants the Prophets, verſe</hi> 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>When this great and laſt trumpet ſhall ſound, mentioned in all thoſe places before cited, and whereof the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> long before this, ſpake, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 27.13.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall all thoſe great things be done, ſpoken of in the ſame places. The Lord ſhall come in his glory, and then hee ſhall ſit in the throne of his glory: the dead both good and bad ſhall be brought before him, and be judged: Then ſhall all the Tribes and kindreds of the earth, even the whole multitude of the ungodly, that ever had been on the earth, and they alſo which pierced him, ſee him, and mourn and waile becauſe of him, and hee ſhall ſend his Angels with the ſound of the ſame great Trumpet, and they ſhall gather his elect together from the four winds, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then there ſhall bee time for repentance no longer: but the great myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, even that great myſtery of the redemption of all Gods choſen ones, the whole houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſpirituall, as he had declared to his ſervants the Prophets, and whereof, they all (that have been ſince the world began) have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, according as it is teſtified of them, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.69, 70, 71, &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. and as their own written propheſies doe ſhew more abundantly.</p>
               <p>And this is that redemption wherewith the Lord himſelfe doth comfort his choſen, hee having foreſhewed all the ſig<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhould goe before the ſame, ſaying, <hi>And when yee ſee theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to come to paſſe, then look up, and lift up your heads, for your redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion draweth neere. Then know yee that the kingdome of God is nigh at hand, Luke</hi> 22.28, 31.</p>
               <p>Now the kingdomes of this world ſo long time uſurped by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs and Antichriſts, ſhall be made the Kingdomes of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>The kingdomes of this world, in reſpect of the creation and workes of God, for ſo by right they did alwayes belong to the Lord, and to his anointed the Prince of the Covenant, though they have been uſurped and polluted by Satan and his powers of wickedneſſe, which now ſhall be removed, and the earth and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens cleanſed; all things ſhall be new, as it is written, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.27. &amp; 60.22. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.1.5.</p>
               <p>This corrupt world ſhall be purged, and made incorruptible, as theſe our corrupt bodies ſhall, and inſtead of corruption and evill,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123383:18"/>
righteouſnes and holines ſhall dwell therein. And ſo in this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration (as the ſtate ſhall be in the reſtitution of all things, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that it is now) it ſhall be another world, not this, and therefore the Scripture calleth it, <hi>the world to come, Heb.</hi> 2.5, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This preſent world is not that world which was before the Flood, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>The world that then was, being overflowed with water, periſhed,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. and yet we all know, and ſo did <hi>Peter,</hi> that (in reſpect of the works of Gods creation of the heavens and the earth) it is the ſame, though in ſome other kind of reſpect, it is not the ſame, but another.</p>
               <p>So the world to come, though it ſhall bee another world farre differing from this world in ſtate and condition, yet in thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of creation, it will be the ſame.</p>
               <p>And therefore it may rightly be ſaid, in the day (when the Lord ſhall come to reigne) <hi>The Kingdomes of this world are made our Lords, and his Chriſts, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others, to whom they belong not, doe now poſſeſſe them: And they with the whole earth, unto the utmoſt ends thereof, by right of inheritance, are the Lords, as it is written, <hi>I will declare the decree the Lord hath ſaid unto me, Thou art my Sonne, this day have I begotten thee, Ask of me and I will give thee the heathen for thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion. Thou ſhalt breake them with a rod of iron, and daſh them in peeces like a Potters veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,</hi> Pſal. 2.7, 8, 9. And again, <hi>In his dayes ſhall the righteous flouriſh, and abundance of peace ſo long as the Moon endureth; hee ſhall have do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion alſo from ſea to ſea, and from the river to the ends of the earth, they that dwell in the wilderneſſe ſhall bow before him, and the enemy ſhall lick the duſt, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 72.</p>
               <p>And the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> declareth, ſaying, <hi>I ſaw in the night vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and behold one like unto the Son of man came with the clouds of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and came to the Ancient of dayes, and they brought him neere before him. And there was given him dominion and glory, and a kingdom, that all people, nations and languages ſhould ſerve him. His dominion is an everlaſting dominion, which ſhall not paſsaway, and his Kingdome that which ſhall not be deſtroyed,</hi> Dan. 7.13.14.</p>
               <p>Again, he having ſpoken of the four Monarchs that in this world ſhould uſurp the kingdome, ſaith, <hi>But the Saints of the moſt High ſhall take the Kingdome and poſſeſſe the kingdome for ever, even for ever and ever, verſ.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>And the Kingdome, and dominion, and the greatneſſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123383:19"/>
of the Kingdome under the whole heaven, ſhall be given to the people of Saints of the moſt High, whoſe Kingdome is an everlaſting Kingdome, and all dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him, verſ.</hi> 27.28.</p>
               <p>This Kingdom of Chriſt and his Saints is to be after the foure Monarchs are ended, as the Prophet doth plainly declare: and that it being once ſet up, ſhall continue much more time then they all, it ſhall not paſſe away, nor be deſtroyed, but remain for ever, even for ever and ever: It is to have no end, as the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven teſtified to <hi>Mary, ſaying, Feare not Mary, for thou haſt found fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with God, and behold thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a Sonne, and ſhalt call his name Jeſus, he ſhall be great, and ſhall bee called the Sonne of the Higheſt, and the Lord God ſhall give unto him the throne of his Father David, and he ſhall reigne over the houſe of Jacob for ever, and of his kingdome there ſhall be no end,</hi> Luke 1.30, 31, 32, 33.</p>
               <p>And according to all this ſpake the Lord before by the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> ſaying, <hi>And it ſhall come to paſſe when thy dayes be expired that thou muſt goe to be with thy Fathers, that I will raiſe up thy ſeed after thee, which ſhall be of thy ſonnes, I will eſtabliſh his kingdom, he ſhall build me an Houſe, &amp; I will eſtabliſh his throne for ever. I will be his Father, and he shall be my Sonne, and I will not take my mercy away from him, as I tooke it from him that was before thee: but I will ſettle him in mine houſe and in my kingdom for ever, and his throne shall be eſtablished for evermore,</hi> 1 Chron. 17.11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
               <p>And in another place the Lord God confirmeth it again, ſaying, <hi>Alſo I will make him my firſt born, higher then the Kings of the earth, my mercy will I keep for him for evermore, and my covenant shall ſtand faſt with him, his ſeed alſo will I make to endure for ever, and his throne as the dayes of heaven, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 89.27, 28, 29.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>My covenant will I not break, nor alter the thing that is gone forth of my lips. Once have I ſworn by my holineſſe, that I will not lie unto David, his ſeed shall endure for ever, and his throne as the Sun before me, it shall he eſtablished for ever as the Moon, and as a faithfull witneſſe in heaven, verſ.</hi> 34, 35, 36, 37.</p>
               <p>And as one Apoſtle teſtifieth from another Pſalm, ſaying, <hi>But unto the Sonne he ſaith, Thy throne, O God, is for ever and ever, a Scepter of righteouſneſſe is the Scepter of thy kingdome, thou haſt loved righteouſneſſe, and hated iniquity, therefore God, even thy God, hath anointed thee with the oyle of gladneſſe above thy fellowes,</hi> Heb. 1.8, 9. Pſal. 45.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:123383:19"/>Many more great and excellent things are ſpoken of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious kingdome of Chriſt, and his Saints, which (as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by all theſe Scriptures) is to have no end, but is to endure for ever, even for ever and ever world without end. And ſhall be manifeſted when the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Angel ſoundeth the great and laſt trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, even when Chriſt ſhall come in his glory, and all his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with him, and then ſhall he ſit in the throne of his glory, as himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>And ſo it is plain, that it cannot bee underſtood of this world, but muſt needs be of the world to come, when all rule, all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and power, all enemies, are ſubdued under Chriſts feet, which in this world are not, nor can be untill the end thereof, as the Apoſtle yet further confirmeth, ſaying, <hi>For unto the Angels ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h he not put in ſubjection the world to come, whereof we ſpeak,</hi> Heb. 2.5.</p>
               <p>By which words he firſt ſheweth plainly, that all their doctrine of the Goſpel tended to an eſtate of inheritance in a world to come, not this preſent world, and that it was not to be in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Angels.</p>
               <p>But as he ſaith, <hi>One in a certain place teſtifieth, ſaying, What is man that thou art mindfull of him, or the Sonne of Man that thou viſiteſt him: thou madeſt him little lower then the Angels, thou crownedſt him with glory and honour, thou didſt ſet him over the workes of thy hands, thou haſt put all things in ſubjection under his feet, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 6, 7. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Pſal. 8.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>And then argueth, ſaying, <hi>For in that he put all in ſubjection under him, he left nothing that is not put under him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But now we ſee not all things put under him</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>But we ſee Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (who was made a little lower th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Angels for the ſuffering of death) crowned with glory and honour, that he by the grace of God might taſt death for every man: for it became him for whom are all things, and by whom are all things, in bringing many ſonnes unto glory, to make the Captain of their ſalvation perfect through ſufferings,</hi> ver. 8, 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Now is Jeſus Chriſt crowned with glory and honour in the throne of God the Father at his right hand in the heavens, where he is to fit and reigne with him untill he hath put all enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1,</p>
               <p>Not onely all the Monarchs and powers of wickedneſſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all enemies beſides, and death w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> now hath dominion over the bodies of the Saints, it being the laſt enemy, as in another place he proveth, ſaying, <hi>For as in Adam all died, even ſo in Chriſt shall all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123383:20"/>
be made alive; but every man in his own order, Chriſt the firſt fruits, then afterwards they that are Chriſts at his comming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then commeth the end</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he shall have delivered up the Kingdome to God, even the Father, when he shall have put down all rule and authority and power.</hi> And then reaſoneth from the words of the Pſalm 110.1. <hi>For he muſt reigne untill he hath put all enemies under his feet: The laſt enemy that shall be deſtroyed, is death, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the Apoſtle proveth plainly, that the Kingdome which Chriſt at his coming is to deliver up to his Father, when all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are ſubdued under his feet, is the Kingdom where he is now ſitting in the throne of God the Father at his right hand, of which <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, Sit thou at my right hand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I make thine enemies thy footſtoole:</hi> and therefore hee calleth it, <hi>The Kingdome,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>The ſupreme Kingdome</hi> and throne of God; not his own, which he is to receive and take poſſeſſion of with his Saints, in the world to come, when all things are put under his feet. Nay, herein he is to be ſetled for ever, as God promiſed his Father <hi>David, I will ſettle him in my Houſe, and in my Kingdome for ever, and his throne shall be eſtabliſhed for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that of which himſelfe ſpeaketh and promiſeth, to his Saints, ſaying; <hi>And I appoynt unto you a Kingdome, as the Father appointed unto me, that yee may eat and drink at my table in my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſit on thrones judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael, Luke</hi> 22.29, 30.</p>
               <p>And where he ſaith again, <hi>To him that overcommeth will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet with my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his throne, Rev.</hi> 3.21.</p>
               <p>And again, <hi>He that overcommeth, and keepeth my words unto the end, to him will I give power over the Nations, and he ſhall rule them with a rod of Iron, and as the veſſels of a potter ſhall they bee broken to ſhivers, even as I received of my Father, Rev.</hi> 2.26, 27. According to Pſal. 2.8, 9. Where the Lord God alſo ſaith of him, notwithſtanding all thoſe his enemies his oppoſites, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy Hill of Sion, verſ.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>By which teſtimonies a plain diſtinction is made between God the Fathers throne and kingdome, and the Sonnes kingdome and throne. In the throne of God no man or Angel ever ſate, nor ſhall ſit, but Chriſt the Sonne of <hi>David (Davids</hi> and our Lord) hee onely obtained it till all enemies were ſubdued. But in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123383:20"/>
throne of the Sonne, the Saints may and ſhall ſit with him, as the Son hath promiſed.</p>
               <p>Now is the Sonne to bee ſubſtitute under God the Father, as his King, his ſpeciall anointed King and firſt borne, to ſit upon his holy hill of Sion, in the throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> to reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the houſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whereof <hi>David</hi> is one. Hee and they his redeemed, ruling the Nations with a rod of Iron. Which throne and kingdome God will ſo eſtabliſh, as that it ſhall remain for ever as the Sunne, and as the Moon before him, even for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver world and kingdome without end, as he promiſed.</p>
               <p>And ſo (God having thus put all things under his Sonne Chriſt (himſelf only excepted) and the Son having reſigned &amp; delivered up the ſupreme kingdome and throne wholly to God the Father) now is the Sonne alſo himſelfe to bee ſubject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.27, 28.</p>
               <p>And herein ſhall the Sonne loſe no honor: for as he is God hee is the ſame for ever, as before, when he was upon the earth; having taken our nature upon him; he prayed and gave thankes, and was obedient: for although he were the Sonne, yet learned he obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as it is written.</p>
               <p>So now hee with his redeemed, his Spouſe the Church, is to bee ſubject unto God the Father, and to honour him as his head, even as the Spouſe his Church is to be ſubject unto him, and to honour him as her head.</p>
               <p>And here now let me ask the Millenaries a queſtion or two, and firſt this; That if theſe things bee ſo, and that the comming of Chriſt, and his delivering up the Kingdome to God the Father, and the end of the world, and reſurrection of the dead, ſhall bee ſo together at one and the ſame time, without any diſtance of time, either dayes or houres between, as <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22, 23, 24, 25, 26, &amp;c. in plain words expreſſeth them.</p>
               <p>Then I ask, Where they will have time or place for their thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years Monarch, which they expect ſhall be between the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, and the end?</p>
               <p>A ſecond queſtion is, That if at the very time of Chriſts comming, the dead in Chriſt ſhall be raiſed, and his elect that are living be changed in a moment, and caught up together with them, to meet the Lord in the aire, and ſo bee ever with the Lord, as the ſame Apoſtle alſo ſaith, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17. Then I ask, Where
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123383:21"/>
they will have more Saints to die and to riſe again from the dead a thouſand yeares after, as they teach?</p>
               <p>A third queſtion, if Chriſt unto them that look for him, ſhall appeare the ſecond time without ſinne unto ſalvation, as it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. Then I ask, where they will have a third time of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſuch purpoſe, which ſome of them imagine ſhall be?</p>
               <p>A fourth queſtion is, That if Chriſt at his appearing, and his kingdome, when he commeth in his glory, and all his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with him, and ſhall ſit in the throne of his glory, and all Nations and people both quick and dead, be brought before him, and judged according to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31, 32, &amp;c. and <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. Then I ask how they can put it off to a thouſand years after his appearing, or make it a thouſand years a doing?</p>
               <p>A fifth queſtion which is this, And if they doe beleeve, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the people and children of this world here marry, and are given in marriage, and die, yet in the world to come, which is to be in ſubjection unto Chriſt, they who ſhall bee counted worthy to obtain the ſame, and the reſurrection from the dead, as Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, ſhall neither marry nor be given in marriage, nor die any more, but be as the Angels in heaven, &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.34, 35, 36. Then I ask how they will make this their opinion (That there ſhall be a multitude of people of all ſorts, as now, poſſeſſe that world after the reſurrection of the juſt, which ſhall for a thouſand years ſpace ſucceſſively marry, and be given in marriage, and die,) to ſtand and agree with that which Chriſt ſpeakes, and not rather be clean contradictory to the ſame?</p>
               <p>And as touching the firſt reſurrection, and living and reigning with Chriſt a thouſand yeares, ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. it is cleare by the very words of the text, that the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh of, and intendeth a reſurrection ſpirituall of the ſoule, which the Saints living here, did, and doe partake of according to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. where hee ſaith, <hi>The houre is comming, and now is, when the dead ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God, and they that heare it ſhall live, verſe</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>And then afterward ſaith; <hi>Marvell not at this: for the houre is comming in the which all that are in the graves ſhall heare his voyes, and shall come forth; they that have done good unto the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evill unto the reſurrection of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, verſe</hi> 28, 29.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:123383:21"/>Where the firſt reſurrection which is ſpirituall of the ſoul, and the ſecond univerſall reſurrection of the body, are both of them plainly and diſtinctly deſcribed.</p>
               <p>And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Saints of the Church of <hi>Coloſſia,</hi> ſaith, <hi>And yee are compleat in him which is the head of all Principality and power, in whom alſo yee are circumciſed with the circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſinnes of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt, buried with him in Baptiſme, wherein alſo yee are riſen with him through the faith of the operation of God; who hath raiſed him from the dead. And you being dead, hath hee quickned, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him, Col.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. hee ſaith, <hi>If yee bee riſen with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things which are above, where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of God, verſ.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>And I ſaw the ſouls of them that were beheaded for the witneſſe of Ieſus, and for the word of God, and which had not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Beaſt, nor his Image, nor had received his mark upon their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, or in their hands, and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, verſ.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>And then ſaith, <hi>This is the firſt reſurrection, Bleſſed and holy is be that hath part in the firſt Reſurrection: for on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power; but they ſhall be Prieſts of God, and of Chriſt, and ſhall reigne with him a thouſand years, verſ.</hi> 5, 6.</p>
               <p>Where the Lord alſo ſpeaketh to living men, and of them, who having their part here in the firſt reſurrection ſpirituall, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the teſtimony of Chriſt, and dying with him (as <hi>Paul</hi> in another place ſaith; <hi>For the rejoycing that I have in Chriſt Ieſus, I die daily.</hi> And again, <hi>For thy ſake, O Lord, are wee ſlain all the day long, and counted as ſheep to the ſlaughter</hi>) may herein be much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in reſpect of the promiſe, that the ſecond death ſhall have no power on them, according to that in <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>Hee that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth my word, and beleeveth in him that ſent me, hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death to life, verſ.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>So here, <hi>Bleſſed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power, but they ſhall bee Prieſts of God, and of Chriſt, and ſhall reigne with him a thouſand years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereby it is manifeſt the Lord ſpeaketh to men living in the body, and of them: ſuch as having their part here in this
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123383:22"/>
                  <hi>The firſt Reſurrection</hi> (for there can be but one firſt reſurrection) who although now, during the time of the reigne of the great Antichriſt eſpecially, which was to be a thouſand yeares at leaſt, they (as touching their bodies) ſhould for the word of God) and witneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, bee beheaded, ſlaine, &amp;c. and for the hope fake in Chriſt, die daily: yet in the ſpirit as touching the ſoule, live and reigne with Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>dying, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold we live, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. Again, <hi>for ye are dead, and your life is hid with Chriſt in God, Col.</hi> 3.4.</p>
               <p>And when the thouſand yeares are expired, and Satan looſed out of his priſon to goe unto the Kings of the earth, and of the whole world, to gather them to the battell of the great day of God Almighty, according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.14. and 20.8.9.</p>
               <p>Then the Lord comming in his glory, all that are in the graves, even every one, ſmall and great, ſhall heare his voyce, and ſhall come forth. They that through the grace and power of the Spirit of God in the new birth and firſt reſurrection, have done good, unto the reſurrection of life eternall, in reſpect of their body alſo, united now to their ſoule, they being found written in the book of life.</p>
               <p>And they that have done evill (thoſe reſt of the dead, that had no part in the firſt reſurrection ſpirituall from the death by ſinne, and ſo, not beeing found written in the booke of life) unto the reſurection of condemnation in the lake of fire burning with brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</p>
               <p>They now have a reſurrection, and live again, though a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dying life, body and ſoule for ever.</p>
               <p>And that the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. cannot poſſibly bee meant of the bodies of any that are to riſe from the dead, as the Millenaries would have it, wee may perceive plainly by the words of the Text, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. where <hi>John</hi> ſaith not, <hi>And I ſaw</hi> the ſoules that were he headed, as if that could bee; neither doth he ſay, <hi>And I ſaw</hi> the bodies that were beheaded, and they lived, &amp;c. But his words are, <hi>And I ſaw the ſoules of them that were beheaded, &amp;c.</hi> that is, of thoſe whoſe bodies were beheaded, of which ſoules he ſaith, <hi>And they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſoule can no more truly be ſaid to riſe from the dead with the body when it ſhall riſe from the dead, nor for the body, then it can be ſaid to be beheaded with it, or for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:123383:22"/>For although in ſome other caſes when bodies and ſoules are living together, it may bee ſaid, as in <hi>Geneſis</hi> 46. <hi>All the ſoules of the houſe of Iacob which came into Egypt, were threeſcore and ten, verſe</hi> 27. in ſuch like caſes as this, the ſoule being the principall part of man, and the body living and moving together with it, may rightly and truly bee named for both; yet in other caſes not ſo.</p>
               <p>And to name the ſoule and ſay, when a body is beheaded, or dieth, the ſoul is beheaded, or dieth; or when the body ſhall ariſe from the dead, the ſoule riſeth from the dead, it is to ſay and ſpeak a very untruth.</p>
               <p>When the bodies of thoſe Saints which ſlept, aroſe from the dead at the time of Chriſts reſurrection, it is not ſaid their Soules aroſe, but their Bodies onely, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.52. <hi>And the graves were opened, and the bodies of many Saints which ſlept aroſe, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto many.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſoule cannot with any truth or ſenſe of reaſonable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, bee named for the body, nor for both in thoſe caſes. Nay, all the Millenarians in the world, how learned or ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall ſoever they are accounted, are not able to prove this thing, except they hold and can prove (as ſome have been ſo bold of late to affirme and publiſh) that the ſoule of man is mortall, and dieth when the body dieth; and ſo lieth dead in the grave with the body, untill the reſurrection of the body, and then ſo to riſe with it, and be named for both.</p>
               <p>For one corrupt opinion, or point of falſe doctrine, brings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes more of the like nature with it.</p>
               <p>But I leave this to their conſideration, and come again to the Text, to ſee what it further ſaith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the four and twenty Elders which ſate on their ſeats in the ſight of God, fell on their faces, and adoring God, ſaid; Wee thank thee Lord God omnipotent, which art, which waſt, and which ſhalt come; becauſe thou haſt received thy great power and brightneſſe.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>NOw, the ſeventh Angel having ſounded the great and laſt Trumpet, the Lord being come in his glory, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world made his, who is to reign for ever and ever
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123383:23"/>
world without end. Hereupon the four and twenty Elders, which are <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets (as the four Beaſts mentioned in Chap. 4.9. are the four Evangeliſts) fall down on their faces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of God, adoring him for that his judgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt and his worſhippers, which they by the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Spirit of Majeſty given them of God, ſpake of and denounced from time to time againſt them, were now juſtified upon them. And the everlaſting Kingdome of the Lord their God, whoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion reacheth from Sea to Sea, &amp; from the River to the ends of the earth, is now ſet up for evermore, according to all that he had foreſhewed them, and by the ſame Spirit ſpoken by them. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they falling down, and adoring the juſtification of God, break forth into praiſes and thankſgiviving, ſaying; <hi>We thank thee Lord God omnipotent, which art, which waſt, and which ſhalt come; becauſe thou haſt received thy great power and brightneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 17.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the Gentiles were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time of the dead to be judged, and to render reward to thy ſervants the Prophets &amp; Saints, &amp; to them that fear thy Name, little and great, and to deſtroy them that have corrupted the earth.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ANd notwithſtanding the rage &amp; fury of thoſe great Monarchs of the world, that like wild Boares of the Foreſt, that roſe up againſt the Lord, and againſt his people and Citie <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and of thoſe Beaſts of the field which ſaid againſt the Lord and his anointed, <hi>Let us break their bonds aſunder, and caſt their cords from us.</hi> And of all thoſe Antichriſtian powers of ſo long continuance, that have with the reſt (to fill up their meaſure) rejected the Lord, and trode his truth to the ground, and made the holy Citie of his Saints as a ſtreet to trample upon. And of all that innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> which that old Serpent the Devill and Satan ſhall at laſt gather together with their mighty men and chiefe Captaines, againſt this great day of the Lord; bringing them down and compaſſing the camp of his Saints about, and the beloved Citie; intending to deſtroy, root out and take the prey and ſpoyle of all.</p>
               <p>Theſe all (who are here deſcribed, as they are alſo in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2. by the name of <hi>Gentiles: And the Gentiles were angry, &amp;c.</hi>) are now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the wrath &amp; judgment of him who with juſtice judgeth. The great day of his wrath being come, and the time of the dead to be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123383:23"/>
judged. Now the Lord, for whoſe glory this day is made, will ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto every man juſtly and truly according to their works and wayes wherein their hearts have walked and delighted.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to his Servants, his Prophets, his Saints and Martyrs that through faith and patience have overcome, their juſt reward which for his name and promiſe ſake is right and due unto them. And next, unto all thoſe heathen Gentiles and people of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; kindreds of the earth, under what name, and of what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of religion ſoever they paſſe, Jewes, Catholiques, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, or other, whoſe hearts are hard, unrepentant and unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, who by their evill deeds have corrupted the earth; their juſt reward alſo, and recompence which to their workes and wayes is rightly due unto them. For ſo much doe the words conclude in ſaying, <hi>And to render reward unto thy ſervants the Prophets &amp; Saints, and to them that feare thy Name little and great, and to deſtroy them that have corrupted the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hereby it is alſo manifeſt, that at the ſame very time when the laſt trumpet ſhall ſound, and the Lord ſhall come in his glory, the dead both good and bad ſhall be raiſed and judged without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtance of yeares or dayes between, the trumpet ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall be raiſed, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>And although the ſalvation of the juſt, and ſufferings of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, ſhall continue for a thouſand, yea and ten thouſand times ten thouſand thouſands of yeares, even for everlaſting, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures declare; yet the judgment and ſentence paſſing, will require no longer time (in the hands of the Lord) then one day, as the Scriptures alwayes expreſſe it.</p>
               <p>And that we ſhould know for certain, that this day will come at the ſame time when Satan with his Armies of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall be upon Chriſtendome, compaſſing the Camp of the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; and fire ſhall come downe from God out of heaven, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them.</p>
               <p>The holy Ghoſt in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9, 10, 11, 12, &amp;c. doth plainly declare it. And to the end that we ſhould take notice thereof, hee ſaith, <hi>chap.</hi> 21.6. <hi>It is done, I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end, &amp;c.</hi> And in chap. 16. upon the ſame comming down of the Kings of the earth, and of the whole world unto the judgement of the great day, it followeth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>It is done.</hi> And in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39. upon the ſame deſtruction of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> it followeth alſo <hi>verſe</hi> 8.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123383:24"/>
                  <hi>Behold, it is come, and it is done, ſaith the Lord. This is the day whereof I have ſpoken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which day will be the laſt day of this world, ſpoken of by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, Luke</hi> 11.24. and whereof Chriſt ſaith; <hi>But of that day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angelt of heaven, but my Father only. Matth.</hi> 24. For although the Lord hath revealed, and men may know the yeare, yet the day and hour can no man know.</p>
               <p>And as in this laſt day, this preſent world ſhall end; ſo in it ſhal the world to come, and the kingdome of Chriſt and his Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, as it is alſo declared, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31, 32, 33, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. And then ſhall be the reſtitution of all things which God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the mouth of his holy Prophets that have been ſince the world began; as it is alſo written, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20.21. There ſhall bee new heavens and a new earth, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be made a praiſe in the earth.</p>
               <p>And great ſhall bee the difference between the eſtate of this world to come which ſhall be in ſubjection to Chriſt, and wherein he ſhall reigne, and righteouſneſſe ſhall dwell for ever world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end; and the now preſent world wherein the heathen and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Monarchs and Antichriſts reigne, and iniquity beareth rule, and dwelleth.</p>
               <p>And for any to teach or perſwade the Chriſtian State now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as ſome in their Sermons and Printed bookes have done, and doe, that the Kingdome of Chriſt and his Saints whereof the Prophets have ſpoken, ſhall be in this preſent world for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares before the laſt day, is to teach and perſwade to a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine againſt Chriſt, and not for him, whoſe Kingdome is not of this world, which is not, nor will be, being corrupt, ſubject unto him.</p>
               <p>Antichriſt and his Clergie of falſe prophets, that have taken upon them as much as ever did any, the name of the onely true Church of Chriſt in the world, have been as a great Monarch in this preſent world for a thouſand yeares paſt already, and let them take it for their portion of happineſſe. But let no true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Miniſters, ſtate or people, bee of ſuch a mind to teach ſuch doctrine, or looke for ſuch a thing here againe; But rather flie the glory and ſhadow of this world, and look for the eternall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123383:24"/>
in the world to come, ready to bee revealed when Chriſt ſhall come at the laſt day, which I verily beleeve (upon the grounds before mentioned) many thouſands now living, ſhall live to ſee. And ſo I reſt their Chriſtian friend, wiſhing them all true happineſſe, grace and truth, and peace in Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now having here a little ſpace, let mee put a queſtion or two more to the Millenaries;</p>
               <p>As firſt, if when God ſhall have created new Heavens, and a new Earth, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a rejoycing, and her people a joy, there ſhall be no more thence an infant of dayes, nor an old man that hath not filled his dayes, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.20. Then I ask, how there can thence an infant or child of dayes, or an old man die, as they will have it in their Millenary eſtate?</p>
               <p>Again, if the reſurrection of the ungodly ſhall not bee till the thouſand years kingdome of Chriſt (which the Millenaries make to be the day of judgement) ſhall be expired, as they teach: Then I ask, what time they will have for that great multitude of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, not riſen from the dead, to be judged? and who they mean Chriſt ſhall be (all that time of a thouſand yeares) a judging? Or how hee can judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and kingdome, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, if the dead be not all raiſed at his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and kingdome, and brought before him to be judged? or why he ſhould need a thouſand yeares or dayes time of pawſing in judgement, or more then one true naturall day, though there ſhall be a thouſand and ten thouſand times ten thouſand yeares of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and ſuffering; yea yeares and dayes, and nights everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, as it is written, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. and ſundry other places.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
